{"classes":["PER","ARCH","LOC"],"annotations":[["BOOK Aldolf Behne The Modern Functional Building.pdf\r",{"entities":[[5,17,"PER"]]}],["Introduction Rosemarie Haag Bletter Adolf Behne s Der moderne Zweckbau (The Modern Functional Building) pre- sciently unmasked many of the ideologies of functionalism, rationalism, and European Modernism of the 1920s. Written in 1923 (though not published until 1926), it preceded the later German publications of Walter Gropius, Ludwig Hilberseimer, Walter Curt Behrendt, and Bruno Taut and sheds much light on them.? Today the Anglo-American audience remains largely familiar with European Modernism through the narrow focus of Henry-Russel Hitchcock and Philip Johnson s The International Style, 1932, although Hitch- cock s earlier Modern Architecture: Romanticism and Reintegration, 1929, had presented a somewhat more varied picture of recent developments. By con- trast, arguments about Modernism were articulated in surprisingly rich and complex ways in the aforementioned European works of the 1920s. Behne's Der moderne Zweckbau is crucial for understanding modernist polernics contextually, especially those later subsumed under the notion of functionalism. In a general sense, the increasing concern with purpose and Sachlichkeit in early Modernism signifies the change from older, aristo- cratic value systems to an emphasis on everyday and common experience as the new paradigm. Behne s text is also helpful in reconsidering some of the standard assumptions and questions about this period, especially the presumption of a visually coherent style. Instead of emphasizing the exter- nal appearance of buildings, German texts dealing with Modernism in the 19208 identified the new architecture through its underlying conceptua premises. Contemporary expression was therefore seen as a reflection of philosophical attitudes toward modernity, and this view allowed for greater visual diversity perhaps only because an exact correspondence between idea and form was difficult to establish. The three-year delay in the publication of Der moderne Zweckbau reveals much about the competitive nature of early Modernism. Gropius had sought Behne s assistance in preparing the Bauhaus exhibition Internationale Archi- tektur in 1923; but when Behne in turn asked Gropius to change the con- tent or delay the publication date of the book of the same title (the first entry in the Bauhausbiicher, or Bauhaus book series, which was projected for publication in 1924) because of its similarity to Behne s own work, Gropius \r",{"entities":[[36,47,"PER"],[314,328,"PER"],[330,349,"PER"],[351,371,"PER"],[377,387,"PER"],[530,552,"PER"],[557,571,"PER"],[614,625,"PER"],[910,915,"PER"],[2025,2032,"PER"],[2044,2049,"PER"],[2080,2087,"ARCH"],[2146,2151,"PER"],[2166,2173,"PER"],[2301,2308,"ARCH"],[2396,2401,"PER"],[2414,2421,"PER"]]}],["refused. Gropius s decision to start a book series hampered Behne s efforts on other fronts as well. When Behne shortly thereafter approached J. J. P. Oud (whose work Behne had promoted in 1922 in his monograph on Dutch architecture) and asked him for material for his own book, Oud responded that he would prefer to have his work published in the Bauhaus book series. He clearly expected more publicity and credibility given the Bauhaus s insti- tutional backing. Nevertheless, books such as Gropius's Internationale Architektur, 1925, portrayed contemporary architecture as did Behne in an astonishingly varied way. Frank Lloyd Wright's Larkin Building and Erich Mendeisohn s equally massive-looking double house in Berlin were included among Inter- nationale Architektur s illustrations. Hilberseimer s Internationale neue Bau- kunst (New international architecture), which appeared in 1927 under the auspices of the German Werkbund, was similarly diverse in scope. Its exam- ples ranged from an apartment house by Jan Wils to housing by Taut, in addition to unexecuted schemes by Russian Constructivists. In Die neue Baukunst in Europa und Amerika (simultaneously published in English as Modern Architecture), 1929, Bruno Taut was also extraordinarily inclusive in his selection of examples. Whereas several of these books alluded to the perceived internationalism of contemporary architecture, only Behrendt s Der Sieg des newen Baustils The victory of the new building style), 1927, treated the new architecture as a style, as would Hitchcock and Johnson s later study.* Notwithstanding his title, even Behrendt presented a varied picture of contemporary architecture, one that included works by Hans Poelzig, Mendelsohn, and Willem Dudok. ie saw Wright's Robie House and Henry van de Velde s theater at the Werk- bund exhibition of 1914 as the key precedents to modern architecture; and he presented an organic plan by Hugo Haring next to Ludwig Mies van der Rohe s De Stijl-inspired plan for a brick country house so that side-by-side they appeared as equally central examples of the new style. But because Ger- man proselytizers of Modernism tended to downplay the aesthetic aspects of architecture, their criteria depended less on visual elements than did Hitchcock and Johnson s work. Reinforcing this attitudinal difference was the fact that contemporary architecture was commonly referred to in Ger- many as Neues Bauen (new building), just as in Holland it was known as Nieuw Bouwen. 5 It is not entirely clear why the term Neues Bawen became prevalent in the 19208. The word modern was more commonly used prior to 1923, as for example in Karl Scheffler s Moderne Baukunst, 1907, or, for that matter, Behne s Der moderne Zweckbau. Possibly under the influence of the general Expressionist conception of the new man, and more specifically the Neues Bauen exhibition of 1920 at J. B. Neumann's gallery in Berlin, and the popu- larization after 1923 of Gustav Hartlaub s Neue Sachlichkeit (conceived by him as a further evolution of Expressionism, nota reaction to it), the term new attained wide currency among the German avant-garde. Taut s Die neue Woh- nung (The new dwelling), 1924, suggests the link to Expressionism. Neu seems to have implied change and the progressivism associated with the new movement more clearly than the term modern. The latter seerns almost to have been perceived as a neutral chronological marker synonymous with contemporary. Behne himself signifies the shift from modern to neu in his Neues Wohnen Neues Bauen (New dwelling New building), 1927, and the emphasis on the new is apparent in the titles of Hilberseimer s Interna- tionale neue Baukunst, Behrendt s Der Sieg des neuen Baustils, or Taut s Bauen Der neue Wohnbau (Building The new domestic architecture), 1927. It is also possible that neu carried political overtones that had prewar origins in Germany. The weekly newspaper of the Social Democrats was called Die neve Zeit. Behne wrote an essay for this paper in 1914 on the rep- resentation of workers in art. His first book (subsequent to publication of his doctoral thesis) was titled Zur neuen Kunst (Toward the new art) and was published in 1915 by Der Sturm. Modern in a political context may have meant simply of the present time, whereas neue Zeit and by implication neu suggested a rupture with past times. Such contextual or regional shifts in terminology do not apply in the same way to the Anglo-American sphere, where modern continued to be the preferred term. It is significant that Taut s Die neue Baukunst in Europa und Amerika, 1929, appeared in its English edition of the same year under the title Modern Architecture. And Behrendt, the author of Der Sieg des neuen Baustils, 1927, later, while living in America, wrote Modern Building, 1937.1 There are, however, subtle variations even within the more general discus- sion of modern developments, as Alan Colquhoun has recently pointed out.'! Whereas in England in the 1950s the avant-garde of the 1920s was generally referred to as the Modern Movement suggesting a degree of activism and ongoing development today we tend to prefer Modernism, a word that seems to denote a historical period. To understand the ideology and intricacies of the modernist debate that fueled the Neues Bauen, one needs to study more closely the polemics of \r",{"entities":[[9,16,"PER"],[106,111,"PER"],[430,437,"ARCH"],[493,500,"PER"],[618,638,"PER"],[639,654,"ARCH"],[659,675,"PER"],[718,724,"LOC"],[791,803,"PER"],[1018,1026,"PER"],[1041,1045,"PER"],[1220,1230,"PER"],[1404,1412,"PER"],[1539,1548,"PER"],[1553,1560,"PER"],[1609,1617,"PER"],[1702,1714,"PER"],[1716,1726,"PER"],[1732,1745,"PER"],[1753,1761,"PER"],[1762,1773,"ARCH"],[1778,1796,"PER"],[1926,1937,"PER"],[1946,1970,"PER"],[1991,2021,"ARCH"],[2266,2275,"PER"],[2280,2287,"PER"],[2421,2432,"PER"],[2653,2667,"PER"],[2715,2720,"PER"],[2917,2923,"LOC"],[2964,2979,"PER"],[3470,3475,"PER"],[3737,3741,"PER"],[3899,3907,"LOC"],[4696,4704,"PER"]]}],["books by the aforementioned German authors. For this purpose Behne s Der moderne Zweckbau is the most revealing text. It fully explores and carefully sets the stage for later arguments and for the development of concepts such as Sachlichkeit (objectivity, functionalism) and Zweck (purpose, function). In this respect Behne s role is comparable to that of Hartlaub in the staging of the exhibition of 1925 on the Neue Sachlichkeit in painting. Beyond that, Behne, a critic of both art and architecture, was also an astute observer of the con- temporary scene. Although his writings do not have the acerbic consistency of Adolf Loos, many of his essays and books contain sharp, perceptive com- ments and critiques of the Werkbund, Expressionism, and the Bauhaus, as well as the work of close friends. He was not a practicing architect, yet he was not exactly a completely detached observer. Bene was a major partici- pant in Expressionist architectural groups after World War 1. Like Sigfried Giedion, he had the advantage of an academic education in art history and a close acquaintance with nearly all of the principal architects of his time. Adolf Bruno Behne was born in Magdeburg on 13 uly 1885, the son of an architect. When he was a year old his parents moved with him and his two older brothers, Erich and Karl, to Berlin. He grew up class districts of eastern Berlin near the Centralvie in one of the working- hhof (main slaughter- house) and attended a Gymnasium from which he graduated in 1905. His academic training commenced with the study of architecture at the Techni- sche Hochschule (Polytechnic school) in Berlin-Charlottenburg, but in 1907 he decided to study art history at the Friedrich-Wilhelm Universitat. After a stay in Italy, he produced his dissertation, Der Inkrustationssti] in Toscana (The incrustation style in Tuscany), in 1912. Among his teachers were Hein- rich Wolfflin (with whom Giedion had also studied) and Georg Simmel, the great philosopher and sociologist. Thereafter he taught in a Hochschule as well as a Volkshochschule (an adult education program), and he became part of the Volksbildungsbewegung (People s education movement). This move- ment was concerned with furthering education outside of academic institu- tions, and it remained an interest for Behne throughout his career. In 1913 he married Elfriede Schneider, the daughter of a railroad engineer, whom he had met through the mathematics club at the university. They had two daughters Karla, born in 1913, and Julia, born in 1921.4 Before the war Behne also belonged to the Choriner Kreis (Chorin circle), a group of young writers, artists, and architects that met on weekends for walks in the woods around the small town of Chorin near Berlin. Max Beckmann and Taut were also members of the group, and Behne formed a 4 long-lasting friendship with Taut.!* Among Behne s earliest articles were those in Die Hilfe the weekly journal published by Friedrich Naumann, a politician, former Protestant pastor, and one of the key organizers of the Werkbund. Naumann had founded Die Hilfe in 1894 as the organ of the pro- gressive wing of the Christian-Social movement. He had been interested in using the arts to improve the quality of products because he believed that doing so would raise the value of labor, improve the worker's status, increase his joy in work, and thus reverse the trend to proletarianization hitherto associated with the advance of capitalism. \"5 Together with the soci- ologist Max Weber, with whom he was closely associated, Naumann rejected the Marxist view that economics is the central factor in social change. Both men stressed the plurality and interdependence of causes. Behne s name appears for the first time as a member of the Werkbund in 1913, the year after he received his doctorate. Before World War 1 he published articles on the work of Peter Behrens and Taut. His articles appeared in Der Sturm, Die Welibiihne, Sozialistische Monatshefte, and Das neue Frankfurt, among many other periodicals. He wrote frequently on the role of the museum in the general education of the public and more specifically on the ambigu- ous nature of the framed picture in the museum setting. Since the museum imposes a change in context on all works of art, he saw the common concern with original art as a false issue. In his essay Das reproduktive Zeitalter (The reproductive era} of 1917, he seems to prefigure Walter Benjamin s well- known thesis about the effect of mass produced images on art.' Behne was also interested in advertising and its wide-ranging effects on culture: he once referred to Mendelsohn s urban buildings as Reklamearchitektur (adver- tising architecture). He did not, however, see eye-to-eye with the prevailing Werkbund policy imposing aesthetic standards on all aspects of daily life. Advertising, he wrote in 1924, was as central to a modern economy as money, and any attempt to control it through aesthetic regulations was bound to be counterproductive in that it would treat advertising as a purely formal problem. On the one hand, Behne did not believe that using art to mask a subject was necessarily good.'? On the other hand, he wrote about films as art as early as 1921, and he included the important role of film in his discussion of pedagogy.' As noted above, Behne s first book, Zur neuen Kunst was published in 1915 by Der Sturm, the major disseminator of contemporary, and particu- larly Expressionist, art. An excerpt from the book titled Expressionistische Architektur appeared in the magazine Der Sturm in the same year. This \r",{"entities":[[318,323,"PER"],[413,430,"PER"],[457,462,"PER"],[621,631,"PER"],[753,760,"ARCH"],[983,999,"PER"],[1144,1161,"PER"],[1174,1183,"LOC"],[1303,1308,"PER"],[1313,1317,"PER"],[1322,1329,"LOC"],[1368,1374,"LOC"],[1623,1644,"LOC"],[1697,1727,"LOC"],[1744,1749,"LOC"],[1945,1957,"PER"],[2345,2363,"PER"],[2489,2494,"PER"],[2514,2519,"PER"],[2551,2556,"PER"],[2741,2748,"LOC"],[2749,2761,"PER"],[2766,2770,"PER"],[2807,2812,"PER"],[2867,2872,"PER"],[2949,2966,"PER"],[3055,3062,"PER"],[3499,3508,"PER"],[3547,3554,"PER"],[3699,3704,"PER"],[3874,3887,"PER"],[3892,3897,"PER"],[4432,4447,"PER"],[4519,4524,"PER"],[4621,4631,"PER"],[5083,5088,"PER"],[5318,5323,"PER"]]}],["essay was among the earliest attempts to define Expressionism, and it certainly was the first to do so within the context of architecture. Behne s description of Expressionism was not narrowly Germanic or medievalizing, and his essay included Cubism and Futurism as equally important aspects of this contemporary expression. In 1915 Behne also wrote an article in Die Tat entitled Der Hass der Neutralen (The hatred of the neutrals), in which he complained about the lack of support for Germany during the early war years. He returned the idea of an avant-garde to its original military meaning when he wrote that those who did not commit themselves were fearful of the new. Behne was hardly alone in this attitude. The sociologist Weber described the war as great and wonderful, and Thomas Mann saw it as purification, liberation ...an immense hope. 2 Behne s position during the war years has led to a diverse set of assess- ments concerning his political beliefs. lain Boyd Whyte in his otherwise exceptionally informative Bruno Taut and the Architecture of Activism, 1982, uses this essay and Behne s association with the Choriner Kreis (among other things) to show that he (and Taut) were essentially conservative.?! Fol- lowing the Marxist, or more correctly Stalinist, argument of Georg Lukacs in his attack on Expressionism of 1934 (by this time he had become an apologist for Stalinism), Whyte finds conservatism endemic. Lukacs viewed Expres- sionism as counterrevolutionary because it was a product of imperialist cap- italism and therefore responsible for fascism. According to the Lukacsian formula, the association of Behne and Taut with the Choriner Kreis estab- lishes them as conservative, because the group's back-to-nature component can be regarded as part of the Wanderv gel Movement, which began in the 1890s. By the 1930s this movement was clearly an extension of the National Socialists nationalism and racialism; however, before World War 1, it was perhaps patriotic but not nationalist. ? As with the Werkbund, however, political uniformity cannot be ascribed to the members of any large orga- nization, By the same token, one cannot say that the Expressionists or mod- ernists were all liberal. A similar restrictive Lukacsian formula led Magdalena Bushart in Der Geist der Gotik und die Expressionistische Kunst (The spirit of the Gothic and Expressionist art), 1990, to categorize Behne as an oppor- tunist because of his later shift in political opinion. ? But not all changes of attitude reflect ulterior motives. Walter Benjamin, for instance, who was generally recognized as a Marxist in the 1920s, had participated in the Ger- man youth movement before 1914.%4 Lukacs s reductive argument was countered in the late 1930s by one of his former friends, the Marxist philosopher Ernst Bloch (they had met in Simmel s seminar). Bloch wrote that Lukacs s opinions were based primarily on literary Expressionism, as opposed to painting and architecture. He argued further that Expressionism did in fact question basic social values and asserted the constructive value of utopianism. Bloch also found the Expressionists' inclusion of folk art from many countries more meaningful than the Neoclassicism that Lukacs had endorsed.* Most contemporary Neo-Marxist historians such as Manfredo Tafuri and Francesco Dal Co cite only Lukacs and not Bloch, thereby overlooking the vigorous debate and dis- agreements about a politically engaged art that took place in the 1920s and 19308. Possibly because of Lukacs s influence on recent literary criticism, his opinions about Expressionist literature have been carried over into the other arts of the period with which, however, he was not as familiar. Whyte is correct when he maintains that a shift in beliefs took place as World War 1 progressed. Some, like Taut, became pacifists. Behne joined the alternative service as a medical orderly during the war. As early as 1914 three of Behne's lectures were published by the educational committee of the Social Democratic Party (spp), and he wrote for the party s weekly, Die neue Zeit. In 1917, on the other hand, he wrote a book that was published under the auspices of the Diirerbund, a fairly conservative educational asso- ciation for the appreciation of art founded in 1902. In 1917 he also wrote an essay in praise of the Russian Revolution. 8 It is clear that at the beginning of his career his interest in a populist approach to art colored most of his associations. However, sometime during these early years he joined the spp, and in 1913 he had begun writing for Sozialistische Monatshefe, which publi- cized the international socialist movement. After the war he joined the uspp, the Independent Social Democratic Party and the schismatic left wing of the majority Socialists; this group had been founded in 1917 to call for an end to the war and to help politicize the labor force.29 Lukacs, in fact, had coupled his critique of Expressionism with an attack on the uspp. In his opinion the uspn s attitude toward revolution, like that of the Expressionists, was half-hearted. Lukdcs s scorn directed at Expression- ists and the uspp reflects the uneasy alliance between these groups and the Spartacists from 1919 on the Communists (krp} and their later extreme doctrinal split. By the late 1920s the kpp and the uspp had become arch- enemies. But in the last year of the war the Spartacists were loosely asso- ciated with the uspp, and in reality the uspp participated in the mislabeled \r",{"entities":[[139,144,"PER"],[333,338,"PER"],[675,680,"PER"],[784,795,"PER"],[967,982,"PER"],[1026,1036,"PER"],[1097,1102,"PER"],[1288,1300,"PER"],[1632,1637,"PER"],[1642,1646,"PER"],[2265,2282,"PER"],[2808,2819,"PER"],[3303,3318,"PER"],[3323,3344,"PER"],[3524,3530,"PER"],[3719,3724,"PER"],[3827,3831,"PER"],[3851,3856,"PER"],[4913,4919,"PER"]]}],[" Spartacus Uprising of January 1919. Both the spp and the KPD were working-class parties. The kpp, however, contained more unskilled and unemployed workers. The parties respective social programs reflected the differences in their makeups. The Social Democrats sought to develop orthodox Marxism into a Volkssozialismus (popular socialism) and Kultur- sozialismus (cultural socialism) within the capitalist system; the Com- munists, however, demanded radical change and regarded any reform as illusory. Much of the energy of the labor movement was dissipated by the intense enmity between these parties. After 1928 the change of policy of the Soviet Communist Party and the Comintern imposed complete sepa- ratism on the xpp, which became openly confrontational with the spp.?! If one talks about the fate of the Weimar Republic and the responsibility for the onset of fascism, a great deal of blame can be meted out not just to con- servatives but also to the Communists for their refusal to form an alliance with the Socialists. Luk cs s simultaneous attack of Expressionism and the uspp in 1934 must therefore be viewed not just in contrast with Bloch s response but even more as an instance of the hard-left approach of the German xpp and its ongoing internecine struggle with the competing workers party, the Social Democrats. By the end of the war Behne had become unquestion- ably associated with the uspp. In rg19 he complained in an article titled Unsere moralische Krisis (Our moral crisis), published in the Soziali- stische Monatshefte, that nothing had changed and that there had really been no break with old attitudes of nationalist arrogance.}? At the same time, Behne, although often critical of German society, retained the Social Demo- crats belief in the possiblity of reform. While some of his books were addressed to a cultural elite, many more of his publications in the 1920s were directed to a larger audience. Among these were his introductions to art and contemporary art respectively, both published in 1925 by the Arbeiter-Jugend Verlag, Die Uberfahrt am Schreckenstein: Eine Einfithrung in die Kunst (The passage to the Schreckenstein: An introduction to art) and Von Kunst zur Gestaltung: Eine Einfithrung in die moderne Kunst (From art to design: An introduction to modern art). His deep commitment as a teacher to the Volkshochschule Movement is another indication of his general agreement with the Social Democrats attempt to develop a popular and cul- tural socialism.*? Does Modernism Equal Functionalism? For many architectural historians, even those who are well acquainted with German developments in the 1920s, Modernism and functionalism have become nearly synonymous.** Within the comparatively brief period of Modernism, however, functionalism assumed many guises. Although it is not within the scope of this essay to do justice to the complexity of function- alist beliefs in modern architecture, some arguments about functionalism are useful to consider in order to understand both the underlying conven- tions of functionalism in the 19208 and the considerable misunderstand- ings that have become embedded in postmodern discussions. Two extreme positions regarding functionalism help to introduce suc- cinctly the conflicting issues of the history of the term and current reac- tions to it. Characteristic of the positive view of functionalism in the 1950s is Edward Robert de Zurko s excessively broad and uncritical history Origins of Functionalist Theory, 1957. Typical of the early postmodernist reaction against functionalism is David Watkin s rather narrowly conceived Morality and Architecture, 1977. The shared assumption in both works is that func- tionalism is synonymous with Modernism. Using a rather circular argument, de Zurko writes that the literature of functionalism consists largely of the writings of recognized functional- ists (such as Horatio Greenough, Louis Sullivan, and Taut). 3* Whereas de Zurko s book is perhaps too inclusive regarding ideas of purpose and utility, Watkin s tone is that of a postmodern scold. He belittles Le Corbusier's Vers une architecture, 1923, because, in Watkin's words, What is simple, suppos- edly functional, and materialistic in aim, light in colour, and immediately apprehensible in form enjoys advantages in terms of health and morality over other different or more complex solutions. Thus it must be imposed on society as soon as possible if we are to avoid revolution. He goes on to insist that the apocalyptic overtones of Le Corbusier s functionalist argument were later exaggerated by Taut in his Modern Architecture, 1929, and cites the fol- lowing passage from Taut to prove his point: If everything is founded on sound efficiency, this efficiency itself, or rather its utility, will form its own aesthetic law. A building must be beautiful when seen from outside if it reflects all these qualities... The architect who achieves this task becomes a creator of an ethical and social character; the people who use the building for any purpose, will, through the structure of the house, be brought 9 \r",{"entities":[[1679,1684,"PER"],[3407,3429,"PER"],[3581,3593,"PER"],[3965,3970,"PER"],[4043,4049,"PER"],[4101,4113,"PER"]]}],["to a better behaviour in their mutual dealings and relationship with each other. Thus architecture becomes the creator of new social observances.** If Watkin himself takes on a moralizing voice in his critique of moralizing theories (in this instance a Puginian trust in social control through architec- ture), de Zurko is more open-minded than most modernist historians in his belief that modern discussions of functionalism show a dual approach: the rational and the poetic. He cautions also that the frequency of statements by modern architects regarding functionalism indicates that functionalism is neither a clear and unchallenged law of architecture nor a spent force, but a vital concept requiring clarification. Important for understanding modern functionalism and Behne s attempt to categorize the various tendencies is de Zurko s discussion of two major nineteenth-century functionalist trends: the mechanical and the organic analogies. The former uses machines as a paradigm for aesthetic theory and is a response to the Industrial Revolution. Although the latter trend draws its references from nature and the former employs models of mechanical production, both could be invoked together. A clear and early example is the theory of the American sculptor Horatio Greenough, who in 1843 proposed a functionalist approach to architecture in order to create what he thought of as a tabula rasa, or hedge against the influence of the older European styles. He believed that functionalism could foster an indigenous American approach to design and recommended, Let us consult nature, and in the assurance that she will disclose a mine richer than was ever dreamed of by the Greeks. He went on to say that the law of adaptation is the fundamen- tal law of nature in all structure. Together with this organic justification, Greenough drew a parallel between natural selection and the production of man-made artifacts in general and machines in particular, If we compare the form of a newly invented machine with the perfected type of the same instrument, we observe, as we trace it through the phases of improvement, how weight is shaken off where strength is less needed, how functions are made to approach without impeding each other, how straight becomes curved, and the curve is straightened, till the straggling and cumbersome machine becomes the compact effective and beautiful engine. * In addition to the organic and mechanical paradigm, Greenough, through his close relationship with Ralph Waldo Emerson, gave his ideas an ethical dimension as well. Behne would also address all three functional concepts present in Modernism the organic, the mechanical, and the social but 10 whereas he described the first two in his role as a historian of the 19208, he only advocated a type including a social dimension. His advocacy of a social functionalism, in fact, resembles Louis Sullivan's polemics. Sullivan s dictum form follows function, stated first in 1888, employed two components of Greenough s functionalism. Its Lamarckian organi- cism is the most evident, and disregarding Greenough's mechanical anal- ogy, Sullivan gave the ethical aspect of functionalism greater importance. Although initially indebted to Transcendentalism as much as to Greenough, Sullivan came under the influence of Chicago School pragmatic realism and John Dewey s utilitarian instrumentalism in the 1890s. These philoso- phies assumed a complex interrelationship between human thought and action and the environment. This interrelationship contrasts with the simple behaviorist model of Pugin, in which the environment affects human action but not vice versa. Hugh Dalziel Duncan explains the Chicago School and Sullivan's dictum thus, Forms arise in attempts to solve problems in social action, form and function are real, not because of their relationship to an essence outside of or beyond action, but within action in society ? The distinctly utilitarian ethics of form follows function do not seem to have on the surface at least a direct relationship with Central Euro- pean ideas in the early twentieth century. However, Beline s stress on the social implications of functionalism, despite his rejection of utilitarian- ism as he understood it, cannot be divorced altogether from the social meaning of utilitarianism or from Sullivan s understanding of function as a social tool. Because form follows function is such an easy-to-recall, alliterative, and concise phrase, it has unfortunately been remembered far too often. In popular usage throughout the second half of the twentieth century, it has usually been forgotten that the phrase was coined by Sullivan, and today it is frequently associated with European Modernism in general or, just as often, with the Bauhaus specifically. In fact, form follows function and Bauhaus functionalism have become imprecise, interchangeable clich s that are used either descriptively by modernists or critically by postmodernists as a presumed shorthand for Modernism. n Hitchcock and Johnson's The International Style so important for introducing an American audience to European Modernism this confu- sion had not yet occurred. Hitchcock and Johnson, in fact, tried to discredit modern functionalism for its lack of aesthetic concerns: Il \r",{"entities":[[314,319,"PER"],[833,838,"PER"],[1268,1285,"PER"],[1830,1839,"PER"],[2452,2461,"PER"],[2499,2518,"PER"],[2565,2570,"PER"],[2882,2896,"PER"],[2909,2917,"PER"],[2999,3008,"PER"],[3126,3134,"PER"],[3259,3268,"PER"],[3270,3278,"PER"],[3344,3354,"PER"],[3580,3585,"PER"],[3653,3665,"PER"],[4653,4661,"PER"],[4821,4828,"ARCH"]]}],["Some modern critics and groups of architects both in Europe and in America deny that the aesthetic element in architecture is important, or even that it exists. All aesthetic principles of style are to them meaningless and unreal. This new conception, that building is science and not art, developed as an exaggera- tion of the idea of functionalism. In its most generally accepted form the idea of function is sufficiently elas- tic. It derives its sanctions from both Greek and Gothic architecture, for in the temple as well as in the cathedral the aesthetic expression is based on structure and function.* They held Hannes Meyer, in particular, responsible for a contemporary doc- trinaire functionalism, because he was an anti-aesthetic functionalist who claimed that the basis of all design must be economic. Lewis Mumford in an essay of 1951, Function and Expression in Archi- tecture, saw the failure of modern architecture, by contrast, to be its lack of symbolic communication. He identified an excessive reliance on a machine aesthetic and a misunderstanding of form follows function as the central problem in the later development of Modernism: Now all this is not to say that the doctrine that form follows function was a misleading one. What was false and meretricious were the narrow applications that were made of this formula. Actually, functionalism is subject to two main modifications. The first is that we must not take function solely in a mechani- cal sense, as applying only to the physical functions of the building. Certainly new technical facilities and mechanical functions required new forms; but so, likewise, did new social purposes and new psychological insights.*! For Mumford the modern period is an age of deep psychological explo- ration and heightened social responsibility. It is not just the age of Albert Einstein, Henry Bessemer, and Frederick Taylor but also the age of Charles Darwin, Henri Bergson, Sigmund Freud, and Pyotr Alekseyevich Kropotkin. Mumford s analysis is similar to that of Joseph Hudnut in his essay The Post-Modern House, 1945.*? Hudnut was then the dean of Harvard s influ- ential Graduate School of Design and was responsible for bringing Gropius to Harvard. He criticized the use of a dogmatic functionalism and struc- tural invention for its own sake. As early as 1931 (that is, before Hitchcock and Johnson), he had complained that the doctrine of functionalism could be obfuscating and mystifying if a rigid utilitarianism became the sole 12 principle of design. He regarded as naive the belief that beauty is automati- cally created by building logically, the shibboleth of form follows function. If this were correct, no school of architecture would have to concern itself with the teaching of beauty; it would be enough to teach economics, busi- ness, and the cost of materials. The present-day misunderstanding of modernist functionalism does not in fact spring from either Taut s or Hannes Meyer's conception; it is based on an overly narrow definition of function as a single issue that is presumed to be a practical design response within a specific building, one that does not seem to embrace environmental, social, or economic factors. In this later, simplistic version of functionalism, biological and utilitarian ideas have become not only hopelessly abbreviated, frozen, and canonical but also nearly meaningless. One problem with interpreting functionalism as if it were a law or mathematical theorem (the belief that there is indeed a specific form for each possible function) is that it is based on a fundamental misappre- hension of design procedures. In truth, a single function if it can ever be completely segregated conceptually from all other functions can be inter- preted by the architect in many appropriate formal expressions. Never- theless, form follows function in its popular conception may be difficult to dislodge because it provides a semblance of rules in an area where there are none. Not all architectural histories that address functionalism are as extreme as de Zurko s in their apparent unpolemical neutrality or as hotly polemi- cal as Watkin s. For instance, Heinrich Klotz in The History of Postmodern Architecture, 1988, makes a fair assessment of the difference between the functionalism of classical Modernism and a later vulgar or doctrinaire functionalism. He even takes time to discuss the less well-known organic functionalism of Haring, a form of modernist functionalism that Behne also deals with at length. The postmodern reaction against Modernism as well as the consequent tendency to present Modernism in an overly simplis- tic form has been most apparent in the Anglo-American sphere, whereas elsewhere attitudes have reflected a calmer evolutionary approach. In this context it is significant that Klotz s book, when it was first published in Ger- many in 1984, was called Moderne und Postmoderne: Architektur der Gegen- wart. The German title suggests that Modernism and postmodernism are simultaneously present in contemporary architecture; in the title of the American version Modernism has been banished. %3 \r",{"entities":[[619,631,"PER"],[814,827,"PER"],[1911,1925,"PER"],[1927,1940,"PER"],[1942,1955,"PER"],[1961,1990,"PER"],[1991,1998,"PER"],[2032,2045,"PER"],[2201,2208,"PER"],[2350,2359,"PER"],[2364,2371,"PER"],[2954,2966,"PER"],[4065,4070,"PER"],[4141,4147,"PER"],[4165,4179,"PER"],[4491,4496,"PER"],[4820,4825,"PER"],[4865,4874,"LOC"]]}],["Whereas de Zurko described the progress of functionalism uncritically, Colquhoun in his Essays in Architectural Criticism: Modern Architecture and Historical Change, 1981, assessed the possible meaning of functionalism in a few words but with far greater cogency: Positivism, in separating pure instrumentality from meaning, impelled architecture simultaneously toward eclecticism and functionalism. Ever since the late eighteenth century, architecture has oscillated between two poles of thought: that according to which all styles are possible and that according to which all styles are forbidden between synchronic and diachronic relativism. But diachronic relativism the belief in the continuous evolution of architec- tural form can be seen, from another point of view, as the continuation of the eighteenth-century search for the origins of architecture. There is still the sense of a return to the primitive statement unsullied by the historical accumu- lation of metaphor. We see then that the origins of modern functionalism lie in a very complex intermixture of the notion of architecture as relative and evolu- tionary and the notion of architecture as based on natural law.** Equally suggestive, Stanford Anderson in his essay The Fiction of Func- tion, 1987, has argued that functionalism is a weak concept, inadequate for the characterization or analysis of any architecture. He continues: It may be useful to recognize functionalism to the extent that one can find some naive functionalist arguments to contrast with Hitchcock and John- son s antifunctionalist rhetoric. However, any serious examination of the buildings at issue will reveal that none of them, whatever the surround- ing rhetoric, can be explained functionally. It was a fiction that function provided a crucial line of demarcation within modern architecture. *5 He goes on to describe functionalism in modern architecture as a specific form of fiction not a lie but a storyline that was used to describe a vision of the world that is richer and broader than the postmodern, truncated notion of functionalism projected onto Modernism. Of course, postmodernists demonized Modernism in the same manner that modernists demonized nineteenth-century eclecticism another form of fictionalizing the past, in this case with Gothic horror stories. Anderson's suggestion for studying the functionalist storyline of the modernists will allow us to comprehend their understanding and self-presentation vis-a-vis theory and architecture in its widest implications. Modernist texts need to be examined, therefore, in order to discover both their constructive and constructed fiction. 14 To date, a general awareness of specific modernist books is inadequate, perhaps because so few of these texts of the 19208 have been translated. Taut s Modern Architecture was the only one of the German books of this time that also appeared in English. Le Corbusier's Vers une architecture, translated into English in 1927, is really his own vision for a new architecture and is not about the work and ideas of his colleagues. In addition, many of the cen- tral texts of this period are not readily accessible. They are usually found in special collections of only the best libraries. It is not surprising, therefore, that the historically important International Style or Giedion s Space, Time, and Architecture, 1941, still form the basis for understanding Modernism. The Background to the Debate in Germany: The Structure and Politics of Education As a Competitive System During the 1920s Germany became the center of Modernism in architec- ture. The creation of the Bauhaus in 1919; the Werkbund Ausstellung Die Wohnung (a housing exposition held at Weissenhof in Stuttgart) in 1927 (with an international group of architects that included Mies, Le Corbusier, and Oud); and the meeting of cram 11 (Congr s Internationaux d Architec- ture Moderne) in 1929 in Frankfurt are only a few of the more publicized events. Germany s centrality in the architectural avant-garde is not entirely due to the presumed liberalism of the Weimar Republic, with which the revolutionary tendencies of the decade are often equated. The prelude to Germany (and Central Europe) becoming the interna- tional focus of modernist theory and debate must be sought, at least in part, in the exceptionally competitive and pluralistic educational system estab- lished in the course of the nineteenth century and fully in place by the end of the century.* This was not the case in France. The Acad mie Royale de Peinture et de Sculpture and the Acad mie Royale d Architecture (which merged in the nineteenth century to become the Ecole des Beaux-Arts) had been cen- tralized under Louis xrv in order to preernpt the power of the guilds. Similarly, the Ecole Polytechnique, founded in the late eighteenth century, followed in the tradition of the older Ecole des Ponts et Chauss es (School of bridges and roadways). Although both the Ecole des Beaux-Arts and the Ecole Polytechnique underwent considerable restructuring over the years, neither was decentralized until after the student protests of 1968. 5 \r",{"entities":[[11,16,"PER"],[1208,1225,"PER"],[1532,1541,"PER"],[1546,1555,"PER"],[3799,3803,"PER"],[3805,3817,"PER"],[3917,3926,"LOC"],[3973,3980,"LOC"],[4186,4193,"LOC"],[4199,4213,"LOC"]]}],["The difference in Germany was not the quality of the schools as such but the structural variation determined by the country s political history. In Ger- many, for instance, the struggle for control between the older guild system and the newer academies was not changed by the fiat of a powerful monarch as it had been in France. Debates about the respective merit of each contin- ued into the early 1920s and the beginning years of the Bauhaus, when the school vacillated between being a lodge for artisans and an elite academy turning out designers for industry. More importantly, because Germany consisted of a large number of inde- pendent principalities, the growth and development of architectural edu- cation differed from region to region. In the late eighteenth century, for instance, Prussia experimented with architectural instruction carried out in an art academy, but apparently because of an overemphasis on rules of taste and purely ceremonial expression, a separate school of architecture was founded in 1799, the Bauakademie in Berlin. Here construction and civic planning were given greater importance. The Berlin Bauakademie was united with the Gewerbeakademie (Crafts academy) in 1879 to form the Technische Hochschule (Polytechnic school). In the course of the nine- teenth century separate polytechnic schools, rather than architecture depart- ments attached to art academies, became the most prestigious schools of architecture, although those within art academies continued into the twenti- eth century. A polytechnic school was founded in Karlsruhe in 1825, in Dres- den in 1838, in Stuttgart in 1840, in Hannover in 1862, in Darmstadt in 1864, in Munich in 1865, and in Aachen in 1870. Still others were founded after Germany s unification in 1871.*8 Even after unification, polytechnic schools remained extraordinarily var- ied. Local traditions, once established, were not readily surrendered. Further- more, member states were not treated equally. The larger southern states, such as the kingdomis of Wiirttemberg and Bavaria, had exacted special priv- ileges not extended to other states. At any rate, the control of civil liberties, the police, and education belonged to the separate states, not the federal gov- ernment. Despite Prussia s attempt in the 1880s to establish educational standards for polytechnic schools in the Reich, it is not surprising that schools continued to differ in their pedagogical emphases, nor that those in the southern states, which had had a strong anti-Prussian history before 1871, were the most liberal institutions. Both the Technische Hochschule in Stuttgart and that in Munich, for example, were less pedantic in their educa- tion than the Berlin polytechnic school, which emphasized memorization 16 and extremely long examinations. The schools in Karlsruhe, Darmstadt, and Dresden were more middle-of-the-road, somewhere between Berlin s con- servative institution and the more liberal ones in Stuttgart and Munich.*? The most important unifying factor among the various polytechnic schools was of course the German language, allowing professors and stu- dents to move from one school to another. Gropius, for instance, attended both the Berlin and the Munich Technische Hochschule. For this reason students and teachers were kept aware of pedagogical differences. Where students were unable to influence curricula, they could certainly vote with their feet. Add to this matrix the polytechnic schools in German-speaking countries among them, those in Vienna, Prague, Graz, Brno, and Zurich and one can see the obvious potential for a lively competition. At the same time, Germany, like most other countries, continued to rely on the older apprenticeship system. But unlike other countries, it also had a Bauschule (building school) or Baugewerksschule (building trade school); in 1957 such institutions were given the more impressive name Ingenieur- schulen fiir Bauwesen (engineering schools for the construction trade). The polytechnic school was the most academically structured of these options, requiring graduation from a Gymnasium, the higher secondary school attended only by those who plan to go on to a university. A diploma from a polytechnic school was also the prerequisite for administrative jobs with the governmental bureaucracy. In this respect, the German polytechnic school was comparable to attending the Ecole des Beaux-Arts or Ecole Poly- technique in France. The Bauschule, on the other hand, required only previous work as an apprentice. In Germany compulsory education ends at age fourteen with education in a Volksschule. For most of those entering an apprenticeship system, however, education continues in a trade school where classroom attendance is combined with on-the-job training. The Bauschule was close in conception to the trade schools set up for apprentices in other fields. Courses were usually given during the winter months when there was little construction, and summers were spent as an apprentice. The Bauschule, therefore, combined academic and apprenticeship training. It was in effect a part-time academy that retained the advantages of practical experience. The Munich Bauschule, the oldest, was founded in 1820, and the Weimar Bauschule was founded by Goethe in 1828. By the early twentieth century, architectural education had attained a hierarchic configuration with the greatest prestige residing in the most 17 \r",{"entities":[[18,25,"LOC"],[148,157,"LOC"],[321,328,"LOC"],[436,443,"ARCH"],[590,597,"LOC"],[1044,1051,"LOC"],[1563,1572,"LOC"],[1607,1616,"LOC"],[1629,1637,"LOC"],[1650,1659,"LOC"],[1672,1678,"LOC"],[1695,1701,"LOC"],[1743,1750,"LOC"],[2260,2267,"LOC"],[2616,2625,"LOC"],[2638,2644,"LOC"],[2898,2904,"LOC"],[2963,2972,"LOC"],[2977,2985,"LOC"],[3166,3173,"PER"],[3521,3527,"LOC"],[3529,3535,"LOC"],[3537,3541,"LOC"],[3543,3547,"LOC"],[3553,3559,"LOC"],[3642,3649,"LOC"],[4535,4542,"LOC"]]}],["academic training. Nonetheless, it was entirely possible for architecture stu- dents to avail themselves of ail three systems polytechnic school, Bau- schule, or apprenticeship really four systems if one includes the architecture departments in art academies. Thus the picture became even more cormn- plex and competitive. Taut, for example, studied at a Bauschule, then was apprenticed to several architects, and thereafter attended selected courses at the Berlin Technische Hochschule. Given the diversity of schools within the Reich as well as the ability of students to attend several schools of the same academic rank in different states and to participate in the various hier- archic levels of architectural training it becomes extremely difficult for the historian to make succinct generalizations about architectural education in Germany. One can only speculate that its basic structural complexity exposed young architects to a variety of competing approaches and philoso- phies, which in turn may account for the intensive debates surrounding architecture in the early twentieth century. The political change after 1918 would not have made an immediate impact, because the structure of these competing and interrelated pedagogical systems did not change drastically. Moreover, the modernists of the 1920s were all educated before 1918, at a time when these varied educational systems were all in place. A comparison of two influential architects and mentors, Behrens and Theodor Fischer, can perhaps explain why certain architects became impor- tant teachers for the generation that came into prominence in the 1920s and how these teachers were affected by their own varied regional and educa- tional backgrounds. Today, Behrens is still unfortunately seen as a proto- modernist to whom Gropius, Mies, and Le Corbusier were all apprenticed. As Stanford Anderson has pointed out, this definition of Behrens is a kind of back-forrnation introduced by such historians as Nikolaus Pevsner and Hitchcock;3 they saw Behrens through the work of his pupils and decided that he was the originator of modern industrial forms. A better case can be made, however, for viewing Behrens as an influential, if somewhat conser- vative, architect who received important commissions from German indus- try as well as from the Reich. His case is also interesting for demonstrating the shift from aristocratic to industrial, corporate patronage of crafts and architecture symptomatic of Germany s late industrialization, which was burgeoning in the early twentieth century and transforming the country into one of Europe s foremost manufacturing centers. Behrens s education as an architect was of the most unconventional sort, even in the context of the German pedagogical system. After receiving his 18 training as a painter, he worked in Munich, where in 1897 he became one of the cofounders of the Vereinigte Werkstitten fiir Kunst im Handwerk (United workshops for art in craft}, one of the several reformist arts and crafts associations that took their cue from the English Arts and Crafts Movement. In 1899 Behrens was one of seven artists invited by Grand Duke Ernst Ludwig of Hesse to become a member of the Darmstadt Artists Colony. Because Ernst Ludwig was Queen Victoria s grandson, he had made many trips to England, where he had come in direct contact with the English Arts and Crafts Movement, and he had commissioned M. H. Baillie Scott and C. R. Ashbee to design rooms for him in Darmstadt. The Darmstadt Artists Colony was the only one of such turn-of-the-century ventures to be orga- nized by an aristocratic patron, as opposed to the artists themselves. On the Mathildenhohe, a hill overlooking the city, Ernst Ludwig wanted to establish a New Athens in order to compete with nearby, more established cultural centers. The artists were paid a salary and were expected to produce a Volks- kultur. Their communal studio building, designed by the Austrian Joseph Maria Olbrich (the only architect in residence), was initially called the Arbeitshaus (house of work) and later the Ernst-Ludwig-Haus. The location of such an exclusive colony on the Mathildenh he above both city and palace, inverting the traditional hierarchy vividly revealed the grand duke s high regard for the arts. It was an arrangement that remains, nevertheless, intrinsically hierarchic. It simply placed the artist at the top of the pyramid in place of the ruler. If Ernst Ludwig expected a trickle-down effect from his New Athens, the architecture and crafts exhibited on the Mathildenhdhe never fostered a Volkskultur. On the contrary, some contemporary critics saw only an expression of luxury in the form of a Gesamtkunstwerk. In 1901, the year of the Mathildenh he s first exhibition, a deficit of 300,000 Marks was in- curred by the Artists Colony; this huge amount indicates that the artists were living like princes in the grand duke s not-so-rich Hesse.5! Similarly, the Wiener Werkstatte went through a series of near-bankruptcies and bailouts by wealthy patrons.%? This is not to question the beauty of many designs made by the Darmstadt group or the Wiener Werkstatte but rather their ability to bring their reforms to a wider audience as they intended. If they had studied the English Arts and Crafts development more diligently, they might have also discovered that William Morris had already encoun- tered the problem of crafts production as something only the well-to-do could afford. 19 \r",{"entities":[[323,327,"PER"],[838,846,"LOC"],[1469,1476,"PER"],[1481,1496,"PER"],[1731,1738,"PER"],[1797,1804,"PER"],[1806,1810,"PER"],[1816,1828,"PER"],[1854,1871,"PER"],[1908,1915,"PER"],[1978,1994,"PER"],[1999,2008,"PER"],[2020,2027,"PER"],[2174,2181,"PER"],[2830,2836,"LOC"],[3158,3170,"PER"],[3240,3252,"PER"],[3422,3441,"PER"],[3714,3726,"PER"],[3962,3982,"PER"],[4446,4458,"PER"],[5359,5373,"PER"]]}],["Despite the Artists Colony s shortcomings, Behrens s contact with this group was important for his subsequent career change. At Darmstadt, Behrens was the only artist who was allowed to design his own house; all other buildings were designed by Olbrich. Without even an architectural apprenticeship, Behrens made the transition from painting and arts and crafts to architecture. He left Darmstadt in 1903 to take over the directorship of the Kunstgewerbeschule (Arts and crafts school) in Diisseldorf. During his Diisseldorf period Behrens met the wealthy, young Karl Ernst Osthaus, who quickly replaced Grand Duke Ernst Ludwig as a more modern patron of the arts and architecture. Osthaus came from a banking and industrialist family and at the age of twenty-two had inherited 65 million Marks. He established the Folkwang Museum in Hagen, an exhibition space for con- temporary art with an interior designed by Henry van de Velde. Between 1904 and 1912 Behrens designed eight projects for Osthaus, including a plan of 1907 for Hagen-Eppenhausen, a garden suburb. Osthaus also became closely associated with the Werkbund and in 1909 helped to create the Deutsches Museum fiir Kunst im Handel und Gewerbe (German museum for art in trade and craft), in effect a Werkbund museum for traveling exhibitions. With Osthaus s patronage Hagen became a new cultural center, significantly in the middle of the industrial Ruhr district. In 1907 Behrens was named the chief architect and designer of the az, then Germany s foremost manu- facturer of electrical products, which had its headquarters in Berlin. His fac- tories for the arc and his designs of the company s electric products were, if not frank industrial expressions, symbolic expressions of industrial might. It was during this period that Gropius, Mies, and Le Corbusier were apprenticed to Behrens (not all at the same time). Each arrived with a differ- ent background, rather characteristic of any group of architects in Germany at the time. Gropius had the most formal education with four years of schooling at two different polytechnic schools. Mies had gone through sev- eral apprenticeships before joining Behrens, and Le Corbusier had attended an arts and crafts school at La Chaux-de-Fonds in the Swiss Jura, where he had initially learned to engrave watches. He arrived in Berlin, however, after an apprenticeship with Auguste and Gustave Perret in Paris. Behrens was not much their senior in terms of actual building experience, yet all chose to work for this artist-architect who had an ability to evoke powerful images. Le Corbusier in his report on German crafts and architecture, published in Switzerland in 1912, writes that Behrens s aEG Turbine Factory was referred to as a cathedral of labor, suggesting perhaps the reason for Behrens s 20 rapid progression from high art at the Mathildenhohe to industrial image- making in Berlin.* Behne would later take issue with Behrens as a modernist. Though less well known today, even among architectural historians, Fischer had a greater reputation as an architect and teacher than Behrens before 1914. Le Corbusier first set out for Munich hoping to work for Fischer, and only when Fischer did not have a place for him in his office did he ven- ture on to Berlin in 1910 (with recommendations and letters of introduction from Fischer). During this period Le Corbusier also met with Hermann Muthesius, Osthaus, Bruno Paul, Wolf Dohrn, and Heinrich Tessenow, all among the more recognized figures of the early Werkbund.5+ Le Corbusier may have preferred to work with Fischer because he dealt with issues of city planning and was much better and more conventionally trained as an archi- tect than Behrens. Fischer had been a student at the Munich Technische Hochschule and served an apprenticeship under Paul Wallot, the architect of the Reichstag in Berlin. In 1893 Fischer established himself as a practic- ing architect in Munich. He moved to Stuttgart in 1901 when he received an offer to teach at the Technische Hochschule there. He returned to Munich in 1909 and taught at the Munich Technische Hochschule until 1928. Among his many students and apprentices were Taut, Mendelsohn, Dominikus B hm, Haring, Oud, Ernst May, Alois Welzenbacher, Fred Forbat, Martin Elsasser, and Paul Bonatz. His Swiss student Peter Meyer wrote in the 1930s that more than two hundred Swiss architects received their training with Fischer. Fritz Schumacher, professor of architecture at the Dreseden Tech- nische Hochschule and the keynote speaker at the first Werkbund meeting in Munich in 1907, referred to him as the real teacher of a whole generation of architects. The historians of the Neues Bauen in the 1920s Behrendt and Gustav Adolf Platz still spoke of him as a great teacher. In 1932 he was one of the few to protest the closing of the Dessau Bauhaus ~ not because he was especially sympathetic to its pedagogy but because he believed on prin- ciple that an experimental school should be allowed to continue. Throughout his career Fischer concerned himself with architectural edu- cation and was disturbed by its academic trend. He insisted on greater emphasis on learning through practical experience. One of his moitoes reveals his openness to his students ideas: I do not have a fixed conviction. I like to hear the opinion of the next generation in order to measure myself against it. * He also encouraged his students to follow their own interests and inclinations in order to gain confidence about their work, and he advised them to look for examples not in books but in their surroundings. 21 \r",{"entities":[[43,50,"PER"],[139,146,"PER"],[245,253,"PER"],[300,307,"PER"],[532,539,"PER"],[615,627,"PER"],[824,839,"LOC"],[913,932,"PER"],[955,962,"PER"],[1434,1441,"PER"],[1501,1508,"LOC"],[1792,1799,"PER"],[1801,1805,"PER"],[1811,1823,"PER"],[1844,1851,"PER"],[1976,1983,"LOC"],[1997,2004,"PER"],[2102,2106,"PER"],[2165,2172,"PER"],[2178,2190,"PER"],[2393,2407,"PER"],[2411,2417,"LOC"],[2418,2425,"PER"],[2585,2597,"PER"],[2693,2700,"PER"],[2707,2722,"ARCH"],[2798,2805,"PER"],[2895,2903,"LOC"],[2904,2909,"PER"],[2938,2945,"PER"],[3029,3036,"PER"],[3116,3128,"PER"],[3147,3153,"LOC"],[3270,3276,"LOC"],[3369,3381,"PER"],[3396,3413,"PER"],[3415,3422,"PER"],[3424,3434,"PER"],[3436,3446,"PER"],[3452,3469,"PER"],[3534,3546,"PER"],[3579,3586,"PER"],[3708,3716,"PER"],[3717,3724,"PER"],[3751,3757,"LOC"],[3815,3826,"PER"],[3862,3869,"LOC"],[3878,3885,"PER"],[3937,3944,"LOC"],[3957,3966,"LOC"],[4094,4100,"LOC"],[4180,4184,"PER"],[4186,4196,"PER"],[4198,4212,"PER"],[4214,4220,"PER"],[4222,4225,"PER"],[4227,4236,"PER"],[4238,4256,"PER"],[4258,4269,"PER"],[4278,4286,"PER"],[4292,4304,"PER"],[4323,4334,"PER"],[4577,4583,"LOC"],[4726,4744,"PER"],[4851,4858,"ARCH"],[5039,5046,"PER"]]}],["Fig. 1. Theodor Fischer, Bird s-eye view of a housing project in Gmindersdorf, near Reutlingen, 1903-1915. Munich, Architektursammlung, Technische Universitat Miinchen. Fig. 2. Theodor Fischer, Bird s-eye view of a housing project in Munich-Laim, 1910-1911. Munich, Architektursammlung, Technische Universitat Miinchen. Photo: Courtesy Dipl. Ing. Klaus Kinold. Fischer, whose own architecture was referred to as South German because of its modest regionalism, was particularly concerned with ques- tions of urbanism and housing. His work has occasionally been associated with the artistic planning principles and the emphasis on picturesque urban views of Camillo Sitte as reflected in the latter s Der Stddte-Bau nach seinen kiinstlerischen Grunds itzen (City planning according to artistic principles), 1889. While Sitte had not dealt with the social and economic issues of plan- ning, his approach was based more on developing principles of psychologi- cal perception rather than on romantic, aestheticized imagery. Like Sitte, Fischer sought a practical aesthetics that was based on empirical studies and anthropological constants.** Appointed as the director of Munich s municipal expansion office in 1893, Fischer had considerable influence on the development of new con- struction. Just as Sitte before him, he was critical of monumental, freestand- ing structures and preferred instead building sequences that maintain an urban texture and form a continuous enclosure. In addition to private commissions he built five schools and three bridges for the municipal gov- ernment during his early Munich period. He received a large number of commissions for institutional buildings, such as museums and theaters. Among his larger projects were the Stadttheater in Heilbronn (t902-1913); the Universitat in Jena (1905-1908), for which Taut produced one of the renderings; the reinforced concrete Garnisonskirche in Ulm (1908-1910); the Hessisches Landesmuseum in Kassel (1907-1913); the Museum in Wiesbaden (1911-1920); and the Kunstgebaude in Stuttgart (1909-1913), the last probably his most superbly sited public building. Fischer completed two houses for Tessenow s garden city of Hellerau near Dresden (1909-1910) and a school project that remained unexecuted. His numerous housing projects include the factory town of Gmindersdorf, near Reutlingen (1903-1915; fig. 1), as well as housing in Munich-Laim (1910-1911; fig. 2). In his Alte Heide housing estate in Munich (1918-1930), executed for workers by a cooperative housing association in response to the postwar housing shortages, he turned to the severe scheme of a Zeilenbau (housing set in parallel rows) arrangement in order to rationalize as many small apartments as possible. It was quite unusual within the context of his previous work. His earlier projects influenced the housing of Taut, May, and Oud. Alte Heide, on the other hand, prefigures the rigidly rationalized Zeilenbau projects of the late 1920s, ostensibly produced to deal with the increasing housing shortage and worsening economy. 23 \r",{"entities":[[16,23,"PER"],[25,29,"PER"],[46,77,"ARCH"],[107,168,"LOC"],[215,245,"ARCH"],[258,319,"LOC"],[347,360,"PER"],[361,368,"PER"],[656,669,"PER"],[817,822,"PER"],[1031,1038,"PER"],[1167,1173,"LOC"],[1212,1219,"PER"],[1297,1302,"PER"],[1600,1606,"LOC"],[1751,1763,"ARCH"],[1767,1776,"LOC"],[1794,1805,"ARCH"],[1809,1813,"LOC"],[1837,1841,"PER"],[1889,1913,"ARCH"],[1917,1920,"LOC"],[1938,1961,"ARCH"],[1965,1971,"LOC"],[1989,1995,"ARCH"],[1999,2008,"LOC"],[2030,2042,"ARCH"],[2046,2055,"LOC"],[2128,2135,"PER"],[2161,2195,"LOC"],[2326,2338,"LOC"],[2388,2410,"ARCH"],[2439,2457,"ARCH"],[2468,2474,"LOC"],[2852,2856,"PER"],[2858,2862,"PER"],[2867,2871,"PER"],[2872,2882,"PER"]]}],["Like the work of Behrens and Josef Hoffmann, Fischer s approach became more conservative stylistically and therefore less influential by the 1920s. Most of his students cannot be called mainstream modernists, but several became pivotal figures in the Expressionist Movement in architec- ture after World War 1, and many turned to social issues of housing. But sore, like Elsdsser and Bonatz, remained traditionalists. Bonatz, who had become Fischer s successor at the Stuttgart Technische Hochschule and who later became a National Socialist, railed against Fischer as a wrecker of order. In the end Fischer regretted the increasing stylistic and political conservatism of the Stuttgart School even though it had originally been inspired by his work. In 1907 both Behrens and Fischer became founding members of the German Werkbund, the association of architects and industrial firms that (according to modernist histories) left behind the retrospective ideals of the Arts and Crafts Movement and looked instead to progressivist notions of art and industry.5? Fischer became the first president of the Werkbund in 1907, and he designed the main hall for the German Werkbund exhibi- tion in Cologne in 1914 (fig. 3). Fischer's low-slung, Renaissance-inspired structure was flanked on either side by the templelike buildings by Behrens and Hoffmann. This group of Werkbund pavilions reveals the relative power of these traditionalists vis-a-vis the younger generation of Gropius and Taut, whose Werkbund buildings were assigned compara- tively marginal sites. Although Fischer occupied a central position in the early Werkbund, he soon withdrew from its ideological struggles and came to believe that this organization for the raising of the production stan- dard should have been dissolved after a few years.%* Julius Posener in his text of 1964, Anfange des Funktionalismus (The beginnings of functionalism), has already shown that most of the found- ing firms such as the Deutsche Werkstatten fiir Handwerkskunst Dresden, Vereinigte Werkstatten fiir Kunst im Handwerk Miinchen, the Wiener Werkstatte, and several publishers were more closely tied to the crafts than to modern industry, even though the intention of some of the members was certainly to move in the direction of design for industrial production.* The group had contemplated holding its first meeting in Nuremberg, site of Richard Wagner's Meistersinger, in part to emphasize a relationship to medieval guilds rather than to industry. In the end the first meeting was held in Munich, home of the Werkbund s first presi- dent, Fischer. 24 fiat ted ae Fig. 3. Theodor Fischer, Main hall, German Werkbund exhibition, Cologne, 1914. Munich, Architektursammlung, Technische Universitat Miinchen. \r",{"entities":[[17,24,"PER"],[29,43,"PER"],[45,52,"PER"],[371,379,"PER"],[384,390,"PER"],[418,424,"PER"],[441,448,"PER"],[468,499,"LOC"],[558,565,"PER"],[600,607,"PER"],[677,693,"LOC"],[776,783,"PER"],[1059,1066,"PER"],[1157,1185,"ARCH"],[1189,1196,"LOC"],[1215,1222,"PER"],[1325,1332,"PER"],[1337,1346,"PER"],[1361,1379,"ARCH"],[1468,1475,"PER"],[1480,1484,"PER"],[1566,1573,"PER"],[1809,1823,"PER"],[2368,2377,"LOC"],[2540,2546,"LOC"],[2590,2598,"PER"],[2622,2637,"PER"],[2639,2676,"ARCH"],[2678,2699,"LOC"],[2722,2753,"LOC"]]}],["In addition to architects such as Behrens and Fischer, the Werkbund included among its founding members an architect who all historians will agree was conservative both aesthetically and politically, Paul Schultze- Naumburg. Hermann Muthesius, who might also be included among the conservatives, was instrumental in the creation of the Werkbund as well, but for political reasons he had stayed in the background during its first meeting, so as not to jeopardize its foundation. As a bureaucrat of the Prussian Ministry of Trade in Berlin, Muthesius had criticized the imita- tion of styles in art and industry in a speech he made in early 1907; this in turn had provoked angry reactions and appeals to Kaiser Wilhelm for his dismissal from the Fachverband fiir die wirtschaftlichen Interessen des Kunstgewerbes (Trade association to further the economic interests of the art industries). Because of the Werkbund s extraordinarily varied makeup and the broad range of backgrounds among its members, by 1914 (that is, the year of its first major exhibition in Cologne), it was already split into hostile factions of arts-and-crafis individualists and progressive rationalists, as well as liberal and conservative camps. It was referred to at the time as an association of the most intimate enemies.\"? Despite the Werkbund s lack of a clear direction, it became an important extra-academic transmitter of architectural ideas through its extensive mem- bership, publications, and exhibitions. Stanislaus von Moos has shown that Le Corbusier appropriated some of the ideas and images he used in Vers une architecture (first published in L esprit nouveau) from prewar Werkbund pub- lications.*? The Werkbund in its very makeup and heterogeneity was a reflection of the complex German educational scene in the early twentieth century. The debate at the Werkbund meeting of 1914 was in fact a political one, but it also hinged in part on a misunderstanding of the word Typisierung (standardization), prefiguring arguments and differences of opinion in the 1920s. Modernism as both practice and ideology was not a uniform concept, but it changed in the course of the 1920s and was constantly challenged from within and without the movement. The Werkbund, to which Behne belonged by 1913, illustrates perfectly the numerous academic and quasi- academic prewar institutions that fostered public discussion of the social implications of architecture and design. Behne, in addition to his association with the Werkbund and his even- tual critique of its goals, was a loyal supporter of the Volkshochschule Move- ment: a crucial but not well known aspect of nineteenth-century German 26 educational reform. The Volkshochschule in Germany evolved in the second half of the nineteenth century and was based on Scandinavian models. It did not fall within the complex system of professional architectural education but added yet another layer to the already pluralistic professional educa- tional possibilities. Volkshochschule teaching was like a mixture of American adult education and the courses taught to workers and new immigrants under Jane Addams at Chicago s Hull House and many later settlement houses in the early twentieth century. It might further be compared to the turn-of-the-century art education movement in Germany, inspired by Alfred Lichtwark, who was appointed the director of the Hamburg Kunst- halle in 1886. Lichtwark directed his efforts especially toward the art edu- cation of young people. Volkshochschule lectures did not require entrance examinations, nor did they lead to diplomas (they were not set up for high school equivalency degrees as some such programs are in the United States). Courses, lectures, and study trips were meant to further the education of the public at large. Behne taught from the beginning until the end of his career within this open-ended, unstructured, and completely nonhierarchic educational program. Behne s central role in the Expressionist Arbeitsrat fitr Kunst (Work council on the arts) immediately after the war may also explain the group s concern in its manifestos with art education outside of estab- lished institutions. Questions about the place of architecture and design that had arisen before the war against the background of a socially complex education sys- tem were not resolved after the war. In his well-known opening manifesto of 1919 for the Bauhaus (which was initially a state school, then a munici- pal school, and finally a private academy), Gropius insisted that only crafts can be taught, not art. He used the medieval guilds as his model of instruc- tion. In 1922-1923 the Bauhaus curriculum began to address the design of industrial prototypes, but at the same time it hardly moved beyond a machine aesthetic; and only from 1928 to 1930, under Hannes Meyer's directorship, did Bauhaus instruction concern itself expressly with functionalism. Under Mies' s directorship (1930-1933), the Bauhaus changed focus yet again toward straightforward architectural training without regard for the integra- tion of the arts, which had been the mainstay of early Bauhaus teaching. Today, however, the Bauhaus is known for its Bauhaus style and Bauhaus functionalism. Gropius later insisted that there was no such thing as a Bauhaus style. He was only partly correct. There were in fact several Bauhaus styles, suggesting an eclectic amalgam of several modernisms. 27 \r",{"entities":[[34,41,"PER"],[46,53,"PER"],[200,224,"PER"],[225,242,"PER"],[531,537,"LOC"],[539,548,"PER"],[702,716,"PER"],[1489,1508,"PER"],[1524,1536,"PER"],[2255,2260,"PER"],[2450,2455,"PER"],[2716,2723,"LOC"],[3125,3136,"PER"],[3140,3160,"ARCH"],[3308,3315,"LOC"],[3329,3345,"PER"],[3385,3405,"LOC"],[3415,3424,"PER"],[3686,3699,"LOC"],[3797,3802,"PER"],[3945,3950,"PER"],[4512,4519,"PER"],[4818,4830,"PER"],[4922,4926,"PER"],[5188,5195,"ARCH"],[5229,5236,"PER"],[5356,5363,"ARCH"]]}],["Behne's relationship with Gropius and the Bauhaus was an uneasy one. As early as 1923 Behne criticized Gropius and the first Bauhaus exhibition for its superficial use of several styles at the same time. When Gropius had a chance to design a new building for the Bauhaus in Dessau, he was asked by his patron, the mayor of that city, to include space for the local crafts schoo!. Thus, he could have brought together in a real sense traditional crafts training with Bauhaus instruction, but by the mid-1920s his pedagogical paradigm had become more technocentric. The two schools remained entirely separate entities within the new building, each with its own entry. Old hierarchies in the actual relationship between the avant- garde school and the municipal crafts school were disguised in the modern- looking plan of the building: it appears as if it has no center, but Gropius s office was in the bridge that both connected and separated the two schools. Behne, Critic of Modernisms Even before the end of the war, in 1917, Behne wrote a critique of the Werk- bund that questioned its nationalist economic goals. He wrote that the Werkbund s attempt to bring art to bourgeois, commercial, and political life would lead only to sentimentality. He considered artless utensils far preferable to designed ones. He further questioned the art-into-life beliefs of the Jugendstil and of the Darmstadt Artists Colony (which continued to form an underpinning of the Werkbund s principles), as well as the Werk- bund s emphasis on economic competition. The introduction of aesthetics to the everyday object does not bring about an improvement in quality, he went on to argue, but turns it into kitsch. Somewhat perversely he stated that he preferred kitsch to the imposition of art on ordinary objects. He concluded (and here his argument is revealed as proto-Expressionist) that art should always remain a separate enterprise. His belief suggested the bifurcation of art and the everyday, so common in Expressionism and probably best known in Gropius's assertion that art cannot be taught. in 1920 Behne criticized the Werkbund again in the pages of Sozialistische Monatshefte. Once more he complained about its obsession with everything artistic, from artistic norms to artistic advertisements. He hoped that the new members on its executive committee (twenty altogether, including Gropius, Osthaus, Taut, Bernhard Pankok, C sar Klein, and Poelzig as direc- tor) would bring about a change. He also conceded that the Werkbund was 28 correct in rejecting Scheffler s Ein Arbeitsprogramm fir den Deutschen Werkbund (A working program for the German Werkbund), which had insisted on a boycott of all foreign products.% After the war Behne became closely associated with the Arbeitsrat fiir Kunst, which was founded in 1918, initially under Taut s leadership, and taken over a year later by Gropius. The Arbeitsrat consisted of a group of architects, critics, and artists and was modeled on the Arbeiterrate of the German Revolution of 1918. It sponsored publications, exhibitions, dis- cussions, and circulars that raised questions about art education, public architecture, and the role of institutions in a postrevolutionary society. Behne became the business manager of the Arbeitsrat in 1919 and wrote the texts of several of its publications.** Although the Arbeitsrat maintained the Expressionist interest in mysticism, utopianism, and art as a transfiguring enterprise, it also became concerned with bringing art to a wider public by sponsoring exhibitions in the taverns of Berlin's working quarters. In March 1919 the Arbeitsrat followed a suggestion made by Taut and Behne and proposed a joint venture with the Werkbund to help with the reconstruction of northern France.* This idea for helping war-torn France is a succinct example of the groups activist pacifism and especially of Taut s constructive utopianism. Behne, however, was not hopeful about the success of this effort. He was afraid that if German architects were sent to France, the French might wrongly assume that the Germans believed that the French did not have qualified architects of their own. The Werkbund, in any case, voted the project down. By early 1921 when the artists of the Berlin Dada group had begun to intensify their critique of Expressionism for its emphasis on individualism and for not producing art that appealed to the worker,** the Arbeitsrat had already disbanded. As it became clear that the Arbeiisrat s expectations for a new society were far from the political reality, a disillusionment and with- drawal from the intense utopianism of the immediate postwar years took hold among its former members. As for the Dada effort to create a public art, it was no more successful than that of the Expressionists. Nevertheless, Dada s use of collages containing elements taken from the mass media, while not necessarily any clearer to the public than the Expressionists use of folk art or children s art, proved to be an immensely fruitful artistic direc- tion and prefigured the other modernisms of the later 19208. Like the Expressionists, Dada artists believed that art could be used to revitalize soci- ety, a recurrent theme in early twentieth-century German art. 29 \r",{"entities":[[0,5,"PER"],[26,33,"PER"],[86,91,"PER"],[103,110,"PER"],[209,216,"PER"],[242,270,"ARCH"],[872,879,"PER"],[958,963,"PER"],[1027,1032,"PER"],[2092,2097,"PER"],[2377,2384,"PER"],[2386,2393,"PER"],[2395,2399,"PER"],[2401,2416,"PER"],[2424,2429,"PER"],[2435,2442,"PER"],[2725,2730,"PER"],[2832,2836,"PER"],[2882,2890,"PER"],[3227,3232,"PER"],[3805,3811,"LOC"],[3916,3921,"PER"],[4035,4041,"LOC"]]}],["In an article in Die Weltbiihne in 1926, entitled An den Verein kom- munistischer Kunstmaler (To the Union of communist painters), Behne engaged in a direct confrontation with John Heartfield on the issue of politi- cal art. The debate was occasioned by an earlier comment Behne had made about an exhibition organized by his friend Otto Nagel, a communist painter, in a store in the working-class district in Berlin-Wedding. Heart- field, then representing the official position of the kpp, insisted that the masses first have to be seized emotionally before art can be discussed. Behne, on the other hand, believed that the best art would, in the end, pro- duce the best political art. The work on view was intended to show the suf- fering of the working class. Behne thought that the working class needed no instruction about its suffering and believed that this kind of art was regres- sive because it used the same means as bourgeois art. During a lecture Behne gave at the exhibition, workers demanded that pictures by Otto Dix showing proletarian women be removed. Their realism was found offensive. The xpp s attitude, Behne thought, was not unlike that expressed by the National Socialists, and he concluded that if one wants to seize the masses, one had better understand their psychology. Behne repeated similar ideas in an unpublished essay of 1932, Sozialistische Kunst (Socialist art). He praised as successful the paintings of the German section of the Inter- national Exhibition of Socialist Art in Amsterdam in 1920, as well as the Frauen in Not (Women in distress) exhibition, organized by himself and Nagel in 1931; the latter was again held in the working-class district of Wed- ding. ! The great irony in this debate was that although John Heartfield was an outstanding artist, the kpp vacillated in its support of his work. In 1921 Behne also became the German correspondent for the English periodical The Studio. In 1920 he made a trip to Holland, probably in con- nection with the International Exhibition of Socialist Art, where he met Theo van Doesburg, Hendrik Berlage, H. Th. Wijdeveld, and Oud. ? At the same time he was preparing a book on Dutch architecture, Hollandische Baukunst in der Gegenwart (Contemporary Dutch architecture), which was published in 1922.7? An excerpt from this book was published in De Stijl. As the various modern art movements were becoming increasingly international in the early 1920s, Behne also made contact with architects and artists from other countries. Through his contact with Laszl6 Moholy- Nagy, Behne had even tried to get Oud a commnission for a house in Berlin. Moholy-Nagy had seen an article by Behne on Oud s work and through him Oud received the commission for a Mrs. Kallenbach. Oud came to 30 visit Berlin to see the site, but the project fell through in 1922.74 It was also Behne who first introduced Moholy-Nagy to Gropius. > In 1920 Gropius met van Doesburg at the house of Taut during van Doesburg s trip to prose- lytize De Stijl. 6 It is revealing that the two figures who in 1922-1923 were instrumental in directing the Bauhaus away from its Expressionist begin- nings Moholy-Nagy and van Doesburg were not known to Gropius before Taut and Behne introduced them to him. Thus the key figures of the Expressionist Arbeitsrat played a direct role in bringing about the change toward international Modernism, particularly the incorporation of De Stijl and Constructivism, in the Bauhaus after 1922. During the early 1920s Behne, as well as Taut, was among the founding members of the Gesellschaft der Freunde des neuen Russland (Society of friends of the new Russia}. Behne thereafter occasionally wrote articles for Neues Russland, the society s publication. In 1923, because of his association with this group, he was invited by the Soviet government to visit Petrograd and Moscow, In 1923 he also wrote one of his most insightful reviews of the first public exhibition at the Bauhaus: The exhibition suffers, I believe, because it takes place at a time when the Bauhaus is in a period of change. The new attitude toward linkage with technol- ogy, that is, standardization, is already recognizable, but does not yet appear with any consistency at all. The small-mindedness of handicrafts is also present and confuses the work, and even turns pure machine form into crafts. ... The rejected decorative principle...celebrates triumphs in other places... why did this happen? In order to show that the new, the so-called Constructivist forms have been mastered. ... The [model] house Am Horn stands among all these difficulties as somewhat uninteresting and unknowing. It is half-luxurious, half-primitive; half-ideal, half-time-bound; half-crafts, half-industrial; half-stan- dardization, half-idyll. It is in no sense pure and convincing, but again an aes- thetic, papery affair. Behne held Gropius responsible for this attitude, because he found the same problems within the Internationale Architektur exhibition that was organized solely by Gropius as part of the larger Bauhaus exhibition. Behne felt that Gropius sought to disguise his uncertainty with an abrupt one-sidedness. Because of Gropius s pseudoradical attitude, sachlich tendencies, accord- ing to Behne, were simply presented as yet another direction. Behne con- cluded that the future of the Bauhaus would depend on whether Gropius 31 \r",{"entities":[[131,136,"PER"],[176,191,"PER"],[273,278,"PER"],[332,342,"PER"],[581,586,"PER"],[960,965,"PER"],[1024,1032,"PER"],[1126,1131,"PER"],[1299,1304,"PER"],[1514,1523,"LOC"],[1853,1858,"PER"],[2060,2077,"PER"],[2079,2094,"PER"],[2096,2113,"PER"],[2118,2122,"PER"],[2337,2346,"PER"],[2444,2449,"PER"],[2543,2562,"PER"],[2564,2569,"PER"],[2592,2595,"PER"],[2625,2632,"LOC"],[2633,2644,"PER"],[2668,2673,"PER"],[2677,2680,"PER"],[2704,2707,"PER"],[2743,2754,"PER"],[2755,2758,"PER"],[2776,2782,"LOC"],[2852,2857,"PER"],[2894,2902,"PER"],[2925,2937,"PER"],[2954,2958,"PER"],[2966,2978,"PER"],[3153,3164,"PER"],[3169,3181,"PER"],[3200,3207,"PER"],[3215,3219,"PER"],[3224,3229,"PER"],[3423,3431,"PER"],[3520,3524,"PER"],[3648,3653,"PER"],[3697,3711,"PER"],[3959,3966,"LOC"],[4045,4052,"LOC"],[4550,4570,"ARCH"],[5024,5031,"PER"],[5054,5073,"LOC"],[5074,5079,"PER"],[5090,5097,"PER"],[5174,5181,"PER"],[5244,5249,"PER"],[5299,5304,"PER"],[5340,5347,"LOC"],[5372,5379,"PER"]]}],["could find his way to an absolute Sachlichkeit: This would allow him to take up all inspirations openly and without prejudice and competitiveness and to incorporate them together with his assistants. This would protect him from dipping into surface features here and there (in five projects Gropius changed his style of representation five times). 7 The same year that Behne wrote this cogent analysis of Bauhaus styles, he assembled material for his most important book, Der moderne Zweckbau. He apparently completed the text in 1923. When he could not find a pub- lisher, he asked Gropius in 1924 to hold back his publication of Interna- tionale Architektur, but Gropius refused. The latter was in fact surprised that as a result Rehne considered him uncollegial and responded that there was room for more than one publication, even if many of the illustrated build- ings were similar. Gropius must have known, however, that a book pub- lished under the auspices of the Bauhaus would have a greater impact on public perception. As noted earlier, Behne encountered further difficulties in assembling the material for his book because of the projected Bauhaus book series. Specifically, Oud no longer wanted to supply Behne with a copy of a lecture because he preferred to have it published by the Bauhaus. * Behne must have found all this extraordinarily ironic. In May of 1923, before the Bauhaus exhibition, Gropius had written to Behne requesting his assis- tance in the planning of the Internationale Architektur exhibition. In the same letter, however, Gropius announced that he could not give photo- graphs of the Bauhaus to Behne because he was already planning a special publication that obligated him not to release illustrations beforehand. While asking for Behne s help with his own project, Gropius (even before Behne s critical review of the Internationale Architektur exhibition) was un- willing to share information. Behne was probably less concerned about any similarity between his and Gropius's books than the prospect of having his serious analysis of Modernism overshadowed by the reputation of Bauhaus publications, a fear that was entirely justified. In 1928, two years after Der moderne Zweckbau eventually appeared and shortly before Hannes Meyer replaced Gropius as the director of the Bauhaus, Behne wrote an appreciative article on Meyer's school in Bernau, near Berlin (fig. 4). In a letter Meyer had informed Behne of his deep interest in the cooperative movement in Scandinavia and its influence on his own work.* In 1929 Behne edited the periodical Newes Berlin with Martin Wagner, an early advocate of cooperative housing associations and later the socialist chief city planner for Berlin. 32 Fig. 4. Hannes Meyer, Axonometric view of the Bundesschule des Allgemeinen Deutschen Gewerkschaftsbundes (ADGB), Bernau, 1928. Dessau, Stiftung Bauhaus Dessau, inv. no. I 1737 D. \r",{"entities":[[291,298,"PER"],[369,374,"PER"],[583,590,"PER"],[665,672,"PER"],[732,737,"PER"],[888,895,"PER"],[1048,1053,"PER"],[1411,1418,"PER"],[1434,1439,"PER"],[1559,1566,"PER"],[1632,1637,"PER"],[1769,1774,"PER"],[1804,1811,"PER"],[1825,1830,"PER"],[2004,2011,"PER"],[2259,2271,"PER"],[2281,2288,"PER"],[2321,2326,"PER"],[2420,2425,"PER"],[2599,2612,"PER"],[2715,2722,"LOC"],[2734,2746,"PER"]]}],["bites Behne was forbidden to teach by the Nazis as early as 1933. This was ave to hig membership on the executive committee of PEN, the ae - eraty organization, which had been founded in gat to fight for free me speech and humanitarian rights, and against racism. pen had express t about the threat of Nazi rule.*! After his dismissal as a faculty mem er wn the Humboldt-Hochschule and as a docent at the Stidtische Berliner Vo! - hochschule, Behne published a number of politically neutral books on i\" historical subjects. Six weeks after the war ended he gave a recta @ tl . opening of the Volkshochschule Berlin-Wilmersdorf, titled Entartete on (Degenerate art). It was about the artists who had been forced to emigrate w : the Nazis. This lecture was published as a book in 1947. Behne died in 1948. That he was forbidden to teach after 1933 does not, in itself, tell us pe cisely what Behne s po itical convictions were. After all, Een Noe we was sympathetic to the Nazis, was forbidden to paint. On the one an , Bel did not leave Germany, as did Taut, Mendelsohn, Gropius, Martin Wagne and many others. On the other hand, Mies, who eventually did emigrate, di so only after he had tried unsuccessfully to work for the Nazis. vs that bi What is clear from Behne s writings, at least up until 1933, is t vat s incisive criticism was rarely held back. Together with his more specialize texts on art and architecture, he pursued his lifelong concern for wider ia - lic education through popular books on illustrators such as Heinrich Zille, who was known for his humorous and satirical drawings of the Berlin pro < tarjat.82 Behne also wrote critical essays about the pedagogical function o their acquisitions policies. me nehne s a vees always have historical, contextual interest, but many of his critiques have not lost their power and meaning for the ne reader. As Fritz Neumeyer wrote in The Artless Word: Mies van der Rohe on tne Building Art, 1991: The most explicit critique of Mies s theme was formulated by Adolf Behne in his work Der moderne Zweckbau.... It ranked among the most important publications up to then dealing with the New Building and has retained its significance as key work on the discussion of the theory of architecture. Behne s merit was that he had undertaken a summary of all the ee impulses that originated in the years from 1990 to 1923 and arranged t em in their contextual sequence, whereby he stressed the various concepts 0 rationalism and functionalism, illuminating their respective dogmas and prejudices. Der moderne Zweckbau Despite its title, Der moderne Zweckbau is not a narrow interpretation of functionalism of the sort ascribed to Hannes Meyer by Hitchcock and John- son, nor of the sort that postmodernists assume defines Modernism. From the outset Behne makes his approach abundantly clear. He defines the original need for building traditionally, that is, as a protective device against climate, animals, and enemies. The first building, he writes, fulfilled spe- cific needs and had a purely functional character. In this sense buildings are essentially like tools. But from the beginning of human culture, he contin- ues, there has been an urge toward playfulness, coupled with the need to be practical. He writes that primitive man was not strictly utilitarian as this double urge is verified in tools that are also beautiful and ornamented. The house is no exception: a house is as much a toy as a tool. What does change over time, in his opinion, is the balance between these two impulses, between function and form. In times when formalism has become para- mount and tyrannical, it is necessary to stress function. Design, no matter what the current emphasis, should always aim for an equilibrium between these two competing factors. Thus Behne did not insist on the primacy of function as such but consid- ered it from a larger historical context that requires periodic adjustment. It could be an adjustment that moved toward function or form, but Behne per- ceived his own time to be so overwhelmed by formalism that he thought emphasis should be placed on functionalism. One might argue at this point that Behne was simply employing a larger picture of architecture in order to give contemporary functionalism historical legitimacy. His extensive expla- nation of the drawbacks of the functionalist position in later segments of the book, however, reveals that he was not a mere advocate of functionalism. His linking the production of tools to the design of architecture is, of course, hardly new. With the rise of archaeology and anthropology in the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries, an interest in relating all human artifacts became increasingly pronounced. This new concern eventually came to include a consideration of crafts in any developmental process. Gottfried Semper s writings, especially his incomplete text on style, are probably the best-known instances of such an inclusive approach.** By the late nineteenth century Semper's influence could be seen in the art histori- cal theories of Cornelius Gurlitt, as well as in Alois Riegl s Altorientalische Teppiche (Old oriental carpets), 1891.% Riegl had been keeper of textiles at 35 \r",{"entities":[[2681,2693,"PER"],[2697,2706,"PER"],[2711,2716,"PER"],[3798,3803,"PER"],[4838,4854,"PER"],[5079,5096,"PER"],[5112,5123,"PER"],[5183,5188,"PER"]]}],["ak he the Osterreichisches Museum fur angewandte Kunst (Austrian museum of applied arts) and thus was well aware of the importance of ol in oP ain ing cultural production. This allowed him to move beyon it e san nt notion of a high period of Roman art in his book Die sparomite e \" rs industrie (Late Roman art industry), 1901. Using late Roman crafts pre : tion as his model, he not only directed art historical studies away rom specific high period but included what used to be called the minor ar = The incorporation of tools and crafts in theoretical considerations ne and architecture was not only affected by new fields of research suc as anthropology but also by the changing value systems of the nineteent ee tury, which now stressed the everyday, bourgeois values of an essen ially postaristocratic society. More importantly, while tools and crafts in an i creasingly industrialized society became the foci of discussion because they were affected by industrial production, production in itself (because i i moved from the artisanal workshop to the factory) must also have assume a larger role in the conception of arguments about developmental * cores Significantly, Riegl s book was about Roman Kunstindustrie (art in fst Behne s balancing of form and function, although it seems a high y cone ceptual binary device, does not take on a hierarchic order. The notion building as both a toy and a tool no matter what the current mn al ances does not imply any cultural progression or regression. He writes thata er at gulf opened up in architecture between formal and functional approat because form and function were separated. Thus, while employing tl se two apparently opposing concepts, Behne objects merely to their segreg tion. The balance between formal and functional building, Behne argues, has undergone a sea change in the last decade with the realization t at a functional building can be formally pleasing and that formal buildings in themselves are not necessarily beautiful. Then he goes on to examine the current condition: Attitudes really had changed fundamentally. Architectural form was seen danger, and fulfillment of function was seen almost as a guarantee a i genesis of a good building. Whereas before people believed that artists ied to be very clever in order to produce good buildings despite function ...that 1s, buildings were again being seen much more as tools. wa Functional architectural concepts replaced formal ones. Functional nt - ings used to be specifically defined by their use, a link between the nee creations of architects and the bare utilitarian structures of engineers an ak technicians. Now every building became a functional building, that is, was tack- led on the basis of its type and function. Fulfillment of purpose became one of the means of architectural design as it had been ever since Otto Wagner in 1895 wrote in Baukunst unserer Zeit: Something impractical cannot be beautiful. ** Although Behne is not an advocate of functionalism, his occasional tan- gents on nineteenth-century historicism do reveal some of the prejudices of a modernist. Yet his belief that function and form must be balanced allows him to be critical of an overemphasis on function, and unlike Pevsner or Giedion in their early writings he does not see current trends as the only course for modern architecture. His model presumes that the present focus on functionalism would, at some point in the future, have to be adjusted in favor of formalism. In this sense Behne s Der moderne Zweckbau is about a modernist theory that contains within it the possibility of postmodernism. The progression of his discussion spreads splendidly in ever-widening circles throughout the chapters of the book. After his analogy of tools and toys to architecture in the introduction, he moves from chapter 1, No Longer a Facade but a House, to chapter 2, No Longer a House but Shaped Space, and to chapter 3, No Longer Shaped Space but Designed Reality. Here he brings us back to the larger social context of architecture, In addition to singling out Otto Wagner in his opening chapter, he also speaks of Berlage s Amsterdam Stock Exchange and the demand for a sach- lich development of architecture in Berlage s collected lectures Grundlagen und Entwicklung der Architektur (Foundations and development of architec- ture), 1908,* He also commends Alfred Messel s Wertheim Department Store in Berlin, which, on first view, he believes to be the most revolutionary work of these three architects (figs. 5, 6). On further reflection, however, he finds that the fulfillment of function in Messel s building is not absolutely sachlich. The department store s emphatic piers, which appear to be the most structural of its elements, reveal their intrinsically decorative nature in the way they merge with an overhanging roof line. Behne sees Taut s com- petition design of rgio for the store's expansion as much more consistent fig. 7), and he agrees w